up next, we have Emily Carr.
Emily, I'll throw it over to you.
Hi, I'm Emily Carr.
There are three things
I wanted to say before I get started.
First, I made my ello debut back in 2020.
Apparently, I hosted a digital salon
that was called Mermaid's
Mischief and Mismanagement,
a poetry hotline.
So in comparison,
this is going to be tamer,
just setting the stage for that.
It was also my birthday back in 2020,
and it's my birthday today.
So I've come to think that I get
to present at the yellow on my birthday.
So I am really happy
to be here with you all.
And then finally, like my art,
my career has made
take it a really kind of strange
and delightful trajectory.
I now and the Wonder interpretation
coordinator at the John
and Mable Ringling
Museum of Art here in Sarasota.
So I'm going to touch on that at
the end, because of course,
that is having a very strong influence
on how I think about my work
and how I think about
digital poetics.
So my eco and I'm
putting the Co in parentheses here.
So it's eco poetics meaning
e poetics
and also economics simultaneously.
My Echoplex essay braids together
surrealist occult practice,
ecological ritual and digital poetics.
A human was here.
I see this essay as an invitation
to put one foot in the embodied world,
and the other in the digital world,
to put modern tools and technology
like hyperlink and hotspot in one hand,
and ancient spiritual technologies
like poetry and tarot in the other.
If there is an argument to this strange,
wild and a little bit messy essay,
it is to advocate for a eco poetics
as an effectively empathetic,
politically awake praxis that wields
all of the human tools fire
mirrors, grammar, mental time travels,
technical reasoning, collective wit,
nested scenarios, smartphones
and computer code while simultaneously
staying vigilant to power injustice
and social and ecological emergency.
So my background is an artist,
and I definitely identify
much more as an artist.
And a scholar is very old fashioned.
I spent my formative years offline.
I prefer to write by typewriter
and by hand,
and I come to digital art objects
very serendipitously.
So I'm interested in
how the two art objects I'm
going to talk about Triple kiss of the Sun
and Snow Angels, Wheel of Fortune,
my model.
Just a kind of different tangent
or offshoot of this conversation
about electronic literature
and online connection connection.
My focus is primarily on citation care
and cross temporal conversation.
While using the web as a venue for access,
archivist and community building.
As a love poet, an ecofeminist teacher,
and a newly minted museum professional.
I'm also interested in exploring
how occult digital spaces
might promote
emotional literacy and imaginative risk.
So my lineage is from the Surrealists
and the avant garde feminist.
They inspire.
I can see very direct connections
from their work to mine.
So, for example,
I'm thinking about Leonora Carrington,
Remedios
Varas, Dora ma and he doesn't fall.
Surrealist feminist who
used occult technologies
like ritual, incantation, meditation,
divination, tarot, astrology, archetypes
to court, surprise, refuse uncertainty,
eavesdrop on the subconscious,
and rethink how desire,
destiny, and selfhood get arranged.
So if spirituality is about affect,
belief and cognition, then for me
the occult is about risk,
ambiguity, and change.
So what I want to do
is leverage the sensory to open up to the
extra sensory.
So we start to experience every moment
as a sacred opportunity
to ritualized our relationship
to the world that we're living in.
All right.
So the first example that I want to
share is
I'm going to talk about is Triple
Kiss of the sun.
And let me know if things aren't working
the way that they should be.
So in the beginning,
this artwork was a love song
and an instinctive howl of rage
to celebrate the death
of one of my mentors
who passed away on May 18th, 2025.
So I started
celebrating Neil's life literally
by going to the beach before dawn
on the full strawberry moon
and throwing oranges at the sea.
I'm mad, I'm sad, and I just keep
sprinting and hurling and running
into the sea to recover my orange over
and over and over again.
Till my grief broke loose.
And that throwing of the orange went
from something that was instinctual
and very animalistic.
And I can show you a picture of it
here. Actually, there's.
Yeah, there I am.
And tell that,
like instinctual, animalistic,
like very physical, embodied
and became something that was more
that was an act of devotion and rage,
an act of intimacy and despair,
of melancholy and of loneliness and love.
So in this moment I am thinking of my body
as the song of my sorrow.
In the weeks that followed,
without really naming what I was doing,
poetry or ritual or even art making,
I started inviting friends and family.
This is actually Neil's widow
and his two best friends.
I started inviting a number of people
to join me,
and throwing oranges in the air
as high as they could.
Filming in slo mo
and sending me the footage.
What I think is really beautiful here is
nobody asks why, everybody just does it.
And in return
I some them each a handwritten postcard
featuring the poem
in which the first orange is thrown.
The poem that incited all of this,
which is Mary ruffles kiss of the sun.
So I start collaging the footage
that I'm getting into video triptychs
and layering
on different kinds of audio
to essentially call these video poems.
There's three of them, of course.
It's a triptych.
And then I start crafting accompanying
essays
that I code into what I call kisses.
So for each of these,
there's the video itself,
and then there's some SAS or kisses
that open audio image and text,
each of which forage into mortality.
Taking life advice from poetry
and symbolic revolution
and live action role
play a la The Battle of Oranges
from 12 century Italy.
So ultimately, as I am
skulking through the stages of my grief
and this you know, my grief is becoming
a multimodal piece of art.
Ruffles poem.
You know that
that original poem that sparked
this all becomes what I like to think of
as an interactive, multimedia
altar that invites tenderness,
courage, and spiritual aftercare.
And so I'm actually publishing
an essay about this piece of work
in the American Poetry Review.
I just got my proofs today,
which was one of the most
excellent poetry, excellent birthday gifts
you could ever get.
And they're publishing it,
like with a QR code so
readers can access this
and interact with it.
And I think that
that I don't know if you all are familiar
with the American Poetry Review.
It is like the poetry publication
across the world, and it looks like an
old fashioned newspaper,
which I really love.
Like, I'll tell people I'm
getting the poetry newspaper.
So it's really exciting
that they're moving forward
into this place
right where you can incorporate,
you know,
digital digital poetics
and have a conversation
that's both in an old fashioned
newspaper and online.
Which leads me to my the second piece
I wanted to talk about.
And someone please let me know
if the screen didn't shift as I clicked.
And so this piece, Snow Angels Wheel
of Fortune, this is part of the digital
exhibition, so you can play with it
if you feel so inspired.
And this is this.
This piece uses
play sent, hyperlink and ritual,
and what I see as an invitation
to invite users
to collaborate with change
rather than bracing against it,
which is what I was struggling with
when I created this artwork,
because my art always starts
from a very personal place.
I am having a problem, I'm struggling
in some way, and I create art
in the absence
of anything else that can help me
to process, to manage, navigate
this moment, I create a piece of art
and then I figure out how to share it.
So I think of this piece.
As for when you've got a nasty case
of Chicken Little syndrome, you're riddled
with existential anxiety, psychic malaise,
your dress rehearsing tragedy.
You're throwing yourself
under the bus mentally.
Your self chatter
is like a bad game of telephone.
So this started with its part aroma,
which is where the occult comes in.
So aroma is the art, science
and magic of scent and mood.
It started out as a snow angel.
Essential oil that mixed frankincense,
orange, mint and almond
that I would gift to people
along with a QR code.
Right a little and I brought it actually,
but I forgot to get it out, but I
so it's a central
that I gift to people. And
the little wrapper
around it contains like the instructions
and the QR code.
So again, I really like this
something that's embodied in physical
combined
with something that's digital and online.
It's this is very playful.
So it's organized around those $0.04.
Everything that happens in these corners
relates to frankincense, orange,
mint, peppermint and almond.
So each of those
sit at a cardinal direction
around this tarot inflected
cosmology, which is the
The Wheel of Fortune card from the tarot.
And each of those scents
is associated with a spiritual meaning.
So there's a doorway
which is frankincense,
a flaming heart,
which is orange, crossroads,
which is peppermint, and a threshold
which is armed.
When you spin the wheel,
you get a fortune.
In this case,
I got the crossroads, which is peppermint.
Once you've got your fortune,
each of these in the corners
clicks onto a prayer
or, sorry, a ritual,
a recipe, symbolism, and a story.
So each spin
I'm thinking of as dealing a fortune
that opens onto a miniature archive.
All of these are inspired by artists
and thinkers whose work has accompanied me
through seasons of personal, professional,
and creative pivoting.
And so there's this really interesting,
to me at least menagerie of artists,
thinkers, makers, writers
who don't really belong together
and who you wouldn't find,
like in the same scholarly conversation
or in, you know,
like the same college course.
There's Anina, Simone, Ross Gay, Flannery
O'Connor, Vincent van Gogh, Nicole Krauss.
So my goal here is that as users continue
to spin the wheel, get a new fortune,
click and open the SATs.
The recipes are literally recipes,
I must say.
I included Flannery O'Connor
recipe for peppermint chiffon pie.
Anyways, as they do that right, it's this.
This cosmology is starting to take shape.
That's cross-genre, cross temporal,
cross-cultural, really cross-pollinate it.
And that was my goal,
that this was kind of
a curated container
for a wild adventure of self-discovery,
which like the other piece,
then there's lots of
this information,
is below
so folks can understand the construction
or what it was like behind the scenes
when I made made this piece of art.
So to bring this full circle, I am now
a wonder interpretation coordinator.
I spend my time thinking about the art
and science of wonder,
which I define as the thrill of discovery
followed by sustained curiosity.
So I've come to see these digital occult
art objects, or like my interest in
what I might want to do in terms of wonder
cabinets or vendor camera.
So those curated collections of
curiosities that are designed to inspire
a document are personal histories,
and catalyze a new kind of community.
Thank you all.
Excellent.
Thank you so much, Emily,
and happy birthday.
What a big day,
It is just really thank you all.